Boris Wintein



SENIOR SOFTWARE DEVELOPER



@thisisboris



boriswintein



+32 472 87 47 98



boris.wintein@gmail.com

SUMMARY

Software developer with an architectural focus with 8+ years of experience. Worked on both B2B and B2C solutions, from dedicated servers to whole cloud stacks defined as code. Driving successful architectural redesigns of complex systems improving metrics all around on CodeClimate. Avid unittester.

SALES PITCH

Brutally and relentlessly focused, driven to write perfect, optimized, beautiful code. High standards define my work, the need for innovation and development defines me.

I adhere to industry standards set by the various interop groups, and if none exist, I'll set my own standard, future proofed, abstract and succinct.

At every turn I aim to improve both software and developers around on every facet applicable. I'm a team player and leader, ensuring delivery and satisfaction for stakeholders and developers.

TECHNOLOGY STACK

In no particular order, cloud of (key)words, which came to mind writing this section.

Linux (Debian, Ubuntu, Mint) PHP, JavaScript, Typescript, Java EE, Python, Go, Angular, VueJS, C#, C, Promises, Async, Apache, nginx, MySQL, MSSQL, Oracle, NoSQL, Docker, Kubernetes, Redis, RabbitMQ, NATS, Natural Language Interpretation, BNF, Pipelines and Middleware, Laravel, Symfony, OsCommerce, Magento, Drupal, Wordpress, Doctrine, Zend, Composer, Propel, MVC, OO, ORM, ActiveRecords, ACL, Dependency Injection, Service-Locators/-Containers, Integration Testing, Unit Testing, Caching, Version Control (GIT), SOLID, Dependency Managing, Event Driven Programming, Modular Design, Scrum, Agile, Test Driven Development, Unit Tests, Domain Driven Development, SaaS, iPaaS, ...

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

SOFTWARE ENGINEER AT QLIK (PHP/GO)

Nov 2020 - July 2024

Worked with my direct manager and tech lead to transform our stack according to the requirements set out by Qlik and it's architects. Reduced our code from a full application to headless API and application.

Named champion of the Runtime Environment, I designed the next major version of this Environment, and defined the architecture needed to move from low-code-to-code compilation with execution runtime to a low-code runtime interpretation engine.

Introduced a tiered architecture completely with the needed components and abstracted services in a loosely coupled, fully configurable and Dependency Injected Runtime Application.

Worked on further expanding our support for native files across the platform (e.g., Interacting with streams from API endpoints and supplying API endpoints with streamed data) and supporting other developers that joined our team with both knowledge-sharing and general support.

Championed and driven the introduction of `Docathons` (dedicated periods of time to document code) and the Guidelines Project for our Service (coding guidelines, but also general knowledge sharing such as dotfiles).

Trained and supported multiple juniors in the art of Unit Testing, OOP SOLID Principles, and general Coding Standards that drive interoperability. Introduced, and presented those teachings to the wider group of devs.

Delivered PoC's on multiple Hackathons that were put on roadmap for full implementation. (E.g., the Interpreter, Slack-UI for interaction with our App, ...)

Part of the "API-DESIGN" team which sets the standards and guidelines for API's within Qlik, both REST and Messaging based (NATS Events). Both did reviews and introduced standards regarding REST-API naming conventions and data-format conventions (e.g., set the standard on both naming and values of date-time/timestamp fields, differentiating between human-readable and machine-readable)

BACKEND ENGINEER AT BLENDR.IO (PHP) (ACQUIRED BY QLIK)

Nov 2019 - Mar 2022

Worked closely alongside the CTO to further build out a PoC low-code platform into a fully-fledged application. Drove the architecture design choices to split up our monolith in microservices.

Redesigned from the ground up how user input was parsed and expressions within were transformed/expanded to their expected values.

Singlehandedly designed and implemented the Native File Support, including how Streams were handled.

Set up the database support of the platform in a scalable, modular way as to be able to quickly add broad support for different database engines and solutions within our platform.

Took ownership of the Runtime Environment, optimized, and improved both performance and maintenance by analyzing problem areas within the environment and library and smooth those out. Introduced a whole set of

patterns to solve the complex issues the environment had with successful outcome. Introduced our own Container (PSR-11) to improve how we handle dependencies, backwards compatibility and more.

Right before being acquired, I created the CloudFormation Stack so we could easily deploy across AWS.

APPLICATION DEVELOPER AT ICONTROLLER (PHP/JS)

Sept 2018 - Dec 2018

Worked on different new importing modules to insert financial data into the application. Added a lot of Q.O.L. and Q.O.U. improvements and overall usability/HTML structure improvements, code optimization and working away code rot present in the application.

PHP CONSULTANT AT PHPRO (PHP/JS)

March 2017 - March 2018

As a consultant I worked on multiple assignments over the course of my employment. Most of these were Magento web shops that needed optimization or new module development. I developed the new Reserve and Go implementation for the Multipharma group and streamlined and solved a lot of bugs in their legacy module code. I was also tasked with performance analysis of the Bel&Bo site and SEO optimization for our own company website.

Another project was feature development for Kan Design's printing and design platforms. This is a Symfony project with a lot of messaging (RabbitMQ) and automated actions (Cronjobs) for automatic rescaling and thumbnail generation etc. for the media that was uploaded and used on these platforms.

Finally, I worked on a lead-distributing platform using VueJS and Vuex. This consisted mainly of creating small API endpoints and corresponding JavaScript services in VueJS.

WEB/APPLICATION DEVELOPER AT THREE-SIXTY MEDIA (PHP/JS)

November 2015 – May 2017

Working in a team of 2 developers, developed an inhouse CMS to easily and create and maintain multiple sites. I maintained and expanded the tailored library supporting it, leading the development of the upcoming major version.

I also redesigned, optimized, and normalized the – sometimes dynamically – generated databases in MySQL, I also implemented our own active records/ORM system which is updated along with the generated databases.

Besides PHP-backend work, I also designed and developed a JavaScript-layer interacting with our API to introduce frontend-editing. This is done in pure (OO) JavaScript with RequireJS and some smaller UI-related frameworks (jQuery-ui, Uniform, Masonry)

BACKEND-DEVELOPER AT SURVEYANYPLACE (PHP/JS)

April 2013 – October 2014

I was responsible for maintaining the API and Management Application in which clients could create and manage both surveys and quizzes. This was done with the Zend Framework in combination with an Angular.js 1.x client-app. Models were handled via PropelORM.

I also designed the API that was used by the frontend-application for displaying the surveys/quizzes on multiple devices.

JUNIOR DEVELOPER AT SUMOCODERS (PHP/JS)

November 2012 – February 2013

During a training period I was responsible for updating and creating modules in ForkCMS for specific use cases at SumoCoders. This was before the switch to using Symfony as a base framework instead of the Spoon Library.

WEBDEVELOPER AT ABO-SERVICE (PHP/JS/HTML/CSS)

November 2011 – October 2012

As one of the main developers I maintained and further expanded an inhouse altered version of the OsCommerce PHP framework. Besides that I did slicing and some JavaScript work delivering new sites for clients. JavaScript work was generally jQuery, jQuery-ui and datatables.js.

EDUCATION AND CERTIFICATIONS

2022	Udemy	Guide to Software Architecture
2022	Udemy	Software Architecture & Technology of Large-Scale Systems
2014	Howest Brugge	1BA Applied Informatics: Systems and Software Development
2013	SurveyAnyplace	IBO Full Stack Webapplication Developer
2012	Cevora	Java EE Developer
2011	ABOService	IBO Web Developer and Designer
2011	Howest Kortrijk	1BA `Devine` Webdevelopment & Design
2010	UGent	1BA Morals & Philosophy